Guide to the Edison Cylinder Collection, 1902-1916 CAM.EDI.1982.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Edison Cylinder Collection
1902-1916
ULS Archives & Special Collections
CAM.EDI.1982.01
5 Linear Feet (84 Cylinders)
The Edison Cylinder Collection represents both the songs and the sound recording technology of the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. The songs range from Christmas tunes to Stephen Foster melodies and showcase American Popular Music through Thomas Edison's innovations.
Access Restrictions
There are no content restrictions for this collection. However, due to the nature of the material, the cylinders are to be handled in a very precise way. They should not be held from the outside, but rather two fingers should be inserted into the core of the cylinder then separated to hold the cylinder in place while handling. The oils and rubbing from touching the outside of the cylinder can do damage to the recording grooves in the wax or Amberol.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection consists of 78 sound recording Edison cylinders. The majority of the cylinders (55) are formatted on Blue Amberol cylinders. Also included are black wax cylinders (13), grey wax cylinders (2), and a purple Amberol cylinder. There are also six cylinders of unknown formats either due to their strange coloring and material, or to their fragility and thus were not able to be removed from their cases.
These cylinders showcase sound recordings from the first decades of the twentieth century. Included are Christmas tunes, instrumental arrangements of popular parlor songs, dances, and a basic selection of Popular American music from between 1902-1916.
History
By speaking the words "Mary had a little lamb," Thomas Edison successfully created the first cylinder sound recording in 1877 using tin foil as the recording medium. A stylus created grooves in the medium that corresponded to sound. This technique is not unlike modern vinyl records and LP's. However, Edison discovered that tin foil was not very durable and often only lasted through one or two playbacks. In the decade before the twentieth century, a switch to soft brown wax was made in the hopes that this material would outlast the tin foil as a recording medium for the spoken word as well as vocal and instrumental music.
When the brown wax proved to be almost as problematic to maintain as the tin foil, Edison switched to black wax in 1902. These black wax cylinders were slightly more durable then their brown wax relatives. They also allowed for standardization of rotations per minute in playback speed making most of the Edison cylinders two minutes in recorded length.
Soon after the wax cylinders became popular, another Edison innovation came about in the form of plastic cellulose. This substance, most commonly referred to in the cylinders as Amberol, proved to be even more durable than the wax cylinders. The most popular version used by Edison was the Blue Amberol cylinder. This consists of a plastic cellulose cylinder with a plaster core. These, along with the wax cylinders, were played on special rotating cylinder phonographs that were able to read the peaks and valleys with a needle, like a modern record player.
With the emergence of the recorded disc, the Edison Cylinders fell out of vogue and were not made after the mid-1910s. Today, the Library of Congress pays special attention to their brown wax cylinders because of the cylinders extreme fragility. Of the surviving formats, these are most at risk of being lost forever. The next most vulnerable are the black wax followed by the Amberol. While both the black wax and Amberol are not as susceptible to mold and temperature fluctuation damage as the brown wax cylinders, they still require special care and housing to maintain their playability.
The Edison Cylinder Collection was gifted to the Center for American Music by its current director, Dr. Deane L. Root. The cylinders were collected by Dr. Root's uncle who had an affinity for old sound recordings. The Center for American Music accepted the gift due to the relevance of the recordings and their historic and research value to the University of Pittsburgh. The cylinders are currently housed in the archive where light, temperature, and humidity can be monitored and controlled.
Arrangement
This collection was left in its original order in the specialized case as well as on the top shelf of the audio case. Because of this decision, there are no series or sections intellectually describing the cylinders in the finding aid.
Music; Cylinder recordings; Cylinders (Sound recordings); Popular music -- United States -- 1911-1920; Popular music -- United States -- 1901-1910; Popular music -- United States -- To 1901; Edison, Thomas A. (Thomas Alva); Foster, Stephen Collins, 1826-1864 -- Songs and music
- "Dixie Medley" (Banjo) (Cylinder EDI 0001)
  Scope and Content Notes
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison Cylinder. The printed ID number on the rim reads 1532. The performer is Van Eps. The inside plaster core is chipped on the edges. The cylinder is in the wrong case. The case lid reads, "California and You (Harry Puck) performed by Billy Murray and Chorus."
  This cylinder has been digitized by US Santa Barbara and can be streamed or downloaded here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr+1=1020&num=1&start=1&query=cylinder634
- "Carry Me Back to Old Virginny", 1916 (Cylinder EDI 0002)
  This item is a Black Wax Edison Cylinder recording. The printed ID number on the rim of the cylinder is illegible. There is a long thin scratch lengthwise across the cylinder. It is not in its original case. The case lid reads "Down where the Swanee River Flows performed by George Wilton Ballard and Chorus." A handwritten label is attached to the case which reads "Carry Me Back to Virginia."
- "Uncle Josh and the Insurance Company", 1902 (Cylinder EDI 0003)
  This is a Black Wax Edison Cylinder recording. The ID number printed on the cylinder is 913. The performer is printed as Stewart. There is a small crack in the wax about 1 centimeter long from the bottom lip of the cylinder. It is not in a case.
- "Don't You Remember the Time" (Cylinder EDI 0004)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison Cylinder recording. The printed ID number is 4003. The performer is printed as Louise Terrell and C. Ballard. There is a small accretion stuck to the plastic cellulose. It is in its original case, however, the lid is coming apart.
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and can be streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr%201=4&query=don%27t+you+remember+the+time&num=1&start=1&sortBy=&sortOrder=id
- "Medley of Southern Plantation Songs" (Cylinder EDI 0005)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison Cylinder recording. Its ID number is printed as 1539. The performer is printed as NY Military Band. There is a small amount of discoloration on the bottom lip of the cylinder. The inner plaster core is cracked and pitted on the edges. The cylinder is in the wrong case. The case lid reads "Climbing Up de Golden Stairs performed by Walter van Brunt and Chorus."
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and may be streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr+1=1020&num=1&start=1&query=cylinder7251
- "The Missouri Waltz" (Cylinder EDI 0006)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison Cylinder recording. Its printed ID number is 2950. The performer is printed as Jaudas' Society Orchestra. There is some mold near the lip of the inner plaster core as well as some minor pitting ad cracking of the core. The cylinder is in the wrong case. The case lid reads "She Said 'Aloha' to Me Performed by Walter van Brunt and Chorus."
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and may be streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr+1=1020&num=1&start=1&query=cylinder492
- "Peaches and Cream" (Cylinder EDI 0007)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison Cylinder recording. Its printed ID number is 1971. The performer is printed as Jones and L. Spencer. There is some moderate mold on the plaster core as well as some pitting and cracking at the edges. Several small cracks appear in the plastic cellulose at the bottom lip of the cylinder. The cylinder is in the wrong case. The case lid reads "Oh! How She Could Yacki Hacki Wicki Wacki Woo (That's Love in Honolulu) performed by Arthur Collins and Byron G. Harlan." There is a handwritten label attached to the lid which reads "Peaches and Cream."
  This cylinder has been digitzed by UC Santa Barbara and may be streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr+1=1020&num=1&start=1&query=cylinder492
- "Let the Rest of the World Go By" (Cylinder EDI 0008)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison Cylinder recording. Its printed ID number is 3955. The performer is printed as Marion Cox and H. Hindermeyer. The cylinder is in a case without a lid.
- "Smiles" (Cylinder EDI 0009)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison Cylinder recording. The printed ID number is 3613. The performer is printed as The Harmony Four. There is some mild mold damage to the inner rim of the plaster core. The cylinder is in a case with no lid.
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and may be streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr%201=1020&num=1&start=1&query=cylinder7123
- "Camp Songs US Army No. 2" (Cylinder EDI 0010)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison Cylinder recording. Its condition is unknown due to the inability to safely remove it from its case. There is severe damage to the bottom of the case which may contribute to this situation.
  This cylinder has been digitzed by Syracuse University and may be heard here: http://digilib.syr.edu/cdm4/item_viewer.php?CISOROOT=/cylinder&CISOPTR=686&CISOBOX=1&REC=13
- "It's a Long, Long Way to Tipperary" (Cylinder EDI 0011)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison cylinder sound recording. The performer and ID number are printed as Farrington and Choir, 2437. There is some minor cracking of the plaster on the inner core at the bottom of the cylinder. It is in its original case.
  This cylinder has been digitzed by UC Santa Barbara and may be streamed or downloaded here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr%201=1020&num=1&start=1&query=cylinder7167
- "A Perfect Day" (Cylinder EDI 0012)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison cylinder sound recording. The performer and ID number are printed as Metropolitan Quartet, 2368. The inner plaster core shows some slight mold damage and cracking at the top edge of the cylinder. The cylinder is housed in the wrong case. The case lid reads, "Vigoroso March, performed by the Newyork Military Band." A hand written label is attached to the lid which reads, "Perfect Day."
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and may be streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr%201=1020&num=1&start=1&query=cylinder7167
- "Yaaka Hula Hickey Dula" (Hawaiian Love Song) (Cylinder EDI 0013)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison cylinder sound recording. The performer and ID number are printed as W. Van Brunt, 2915. There is a fair amount of mold discoloration spread over the plastic cellulose. The cylinder is housed in a case without a lid.
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and may be streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr+1=1020&num=1&start=1&query=cylinder879
- "Dreamy Hawaii-Waltz" (Cylinder EDI 0014)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison cylinder sound recording. The performer and ID number are printed as Waikiki Hawaiian Orchestra, 4419. There is some slight mold damage to the inner plaster core at the edges. The cylinder is housed in a case with no lid.
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and may be streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr%201=21&query=hawaii+songs+music&num=1&start=14&sortBy=&sortOrder=ia
- "Don't Bite the Hand That's Feeding You", 1902 (Cylinder EDI 0015)
  This is a Black Wax Edison cylinder sound recording. The performer and ID number are printed as Campbell and Burr, 3378. The inner core has severe mold damage. The cylinder is housed in the wrong case. The case lid reads, "When You're all Dressed up and No Place to Go - The Beauty Shop, performed by Billy Murray."
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and may be streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr%201=1020&num=1&start=1&query=cylinder8020
- "Napoli" (Cylinder EDI 0016)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison cylinder sound recording. The performer and ID number are printed as Imperial Marimba Band, 4180. There is some slight mold damage to the bottom rim of the inner core. The cylinder is housed in a case with no lid.
  This cylinder has been digitzed by UC Santa Barbara and may be streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr+1=1020&num=1&start=1&query=cylinder1124
- "Waiting Down by the Mississippi Shore" (Cylinder EDI 0017)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison cylinder sound recording. The performer and ID number are printed as Campbell and Gillette, 1959. There is some slight cracking of the inner plaster core near the edges. The lid is in fragile condition but still legible. The cylinder is in its original case.
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and may be streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr+1=1020&num=1&start=1&query=cylinder805
- "Silver Bell" (Cylinder EDI 0018)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison cylinder sound recording. The printed performer and ID number are Ada Jones and Murray, 1524. There is some moderate mold damage and cracking of the plaster core at the edges. The cylinder is housed in a case with no lid.
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and may be streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr+1=1020&num=1&start=1&query=cylinder626
- "Christmas Bells" (Cylinder EDI 0019)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison cylinder sound recording. The printed performer and ID number are P. Gayler, 3870. There is some slight mold damage and cracking to inner plaster core. The printed lettering on the plastic is fading. The cylinder is in its original case although the lid appears to have water damage and the label is beginning to fade.
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and may be streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr+1=1020&num=1&query=cylinder5985
- "My Waikiki Mermaid Hula Medley" (Cylinder EDI 0020)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison cylinder sound recording. The printed performer and ID number are Waikiki Hawaiian Orchestra, 3227. There is some moderate mold damage and pitting of inner plaster core on the edges. Something has been spilled and dried on the surface of the plastic. This cylinder is housed in the wrong case. The lid reads, "Something Seems Tingle-ingleing-High Jinks by Walter Van Bru[nt]." There is also a smell of mold coming from the case.
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and may be downloaded or streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr%201=4&query=mermaid&num=1&start=1&sortBy=&sortOrder=id
- "You're a Million Miles From Nowhere" (Cylinder EDI 0021)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison cylinder sound recording. The performer and ID number are printed as W. Bonner, 3982. There is some slight mold damage to the inner plaster core. The plastic has small vertical cracks in three places on the bottom rim. The plastic has also faded to light blue on the bottom and top rims of the cylinder. The cylinder is in its original case.
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and may be streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr+1=1020&num=1&start=1&query=cylinder6743
- "Casey Jones" (Cylinder EDI 0022)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison cylinder sound recording. The performer and ID number are printed as B. Murray and Choir, 1550. A large portion of the inner plaster core has cracked away and is gone. The cylinder is quite dirty and wrapped in paper instead of a case.
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and may be downloaded or streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr+1=1020&num=1&start=1&query=cylinder636
- "Mother", 1902 (Cylinder EDI 0023)
  This is an Edison cylinder sound recording of an unknown type. The performer and ID number are printed as Burr, 3351. It is light blue in color. Whether this is due to environmental wear or manufacturing is unknown. The case does not have a lid.
- "California and You" (Cylinder EDI 0024)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison cylinder sound recording. The performer and ID number are printed as Murray and Choir, 2501. There is some very slight pitting of inner plaster core at the edges. The cylinder is housed in original case after transferring.
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and my be downloaded or streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr+1=1020&num=1&start=1&query=cylinder903
- "Mother Machree Violin" (Cylinder EDI 0025)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison cylinder sound recording. The performer and ID number are printed as Charles D'Almaine, 2419. There is some slight pitting of the inner plaster core at the bottom edge. The cylinder is in its original case.
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and may be streamed here: cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr+1=1020&num=1&start=1&query=cylinder6551
- "By the Light of the Silvery Moon" (Cylinder EDI 0026)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison cylinder sound recording. The performer and ID are printed as, Ada Jones and Chorus, 1521. The cylinder is in its original case after transferring.
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and may be streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr%201=1020&num=1&start=1&query=cylinder0605
- "In the Town Where I was Born" (Cylinder EDI 0027)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison cylinder sound recording. The performer and ID number are printed as, McCormack and Chorus, 2304. There is some very slight mold damage in places on the plastic. The case has no lid.
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and may be streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr+1=1020&num=1&start=1&query=cylinder7247
- "Yellow Dog Blues Fox Trot" (Cylinder EDI 0028)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison cylinder sound recording. The performer and ID number are printed as, H. Raderman's Jazz Orchestra, 3991. There is some slight darkening of the plastic in places. The case has no bottom or lid.
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and may be streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr%201=1016&query=yellow+dog+blues&num=1&start=1&sortBy=&sortOrder=id
- "Sing of Love" (Cylinder EDI 0029)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison cylinder sound recording. The performer and ID number are printed as, Venetian Instrumental Quartet, 2473. There is some slight darkening of the plastic at the top edge of the cylinder. The cylinder is in its original case after transferring.
- "Over There", 1902 (Cylinder EDI 0030)
  This is an Edison cylinder sound recording of an unknown type. The performer and ID number are printed as Quartette, 3412. The cylinder is light blue whether from environmental wear or manufacturing is unknown. There is some slight rust on inner metal core. The cylinder is in the wrong case. The lid reads, "The Jolly Coppersmith."
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and may be streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr%201=1016&query=over+there+cohan&num=1&start=2&sortBy=&sortOrder=ia
- "Rainbow" (Cylinder EDI 0031)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison cylinder sound recording. The performer and ID number are printed as, Ada Jones and Murray, 1884. There is some darkening of the inner plaster core at the edges. The case has no lid.
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and may be streamed or downloaded here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr+1=1020&num=1&start=1&query=cylinder193
- "How Could Washington be a Married Man" (Cylinder EDI 0032)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison cylinder sound recording. The performer and ID number are printed as, M. J. O'Connell, 3086. There is some very slight pitting around the top edges of the inner plaster core. The cylinder is in its original case.
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and may be streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr+1=1020&num=1&start=1&query=cylinder5402
- "Joan of Arc, They are Calling You", 1902 (Cylinder EDI 0033)
  This is an Edison cylinder sound recording of an unknown type. The performer and ID number are printed as, Gillette, 3414. This cylinder is light blue whether from environmental wears or manufacturing is unknown. The cylinder is in the wrong case. The lid reads, "The Missouri Waltz."
- "Silver Threads Among the Gold" (Cylinder EDI 0034)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison cylinder sound recording. The performer and ID number are printed as, Oakland, 1547. There is some slight pitting of the inner plaster core on the top edge. A large piece of the inner plaster core is missing from the bottom edge which has caused a slight malformation in the plastic. The cylinder is in its original case. The case lid appears to be water damaged.
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and may be streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr+1=1020&num=1&start=1&query=cylinder0615
- "Dream of the Tyrolienne" (Cylinder EDI 0035)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison cylinder sound recording. The performer and ID number are printed as, Venetian Instrumental Orchestra, 1795. The cylinder was not able to be removed from the case for inspection. The cylinder is in the wrong case. The case lid reads, "I'm on My Way to Dublin."
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and may be streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr+1=1020&num=1&start=1&query=cylinder766
- "You'd be Surprised" (Cylinder EDI 0036)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison cylinder sound recording. The performer and ID number are printed as, B. Murray, 3964. There is some slight pitting of inner plaster core at the bottom edge. The case has no lid.
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and maybe be streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr%201=1020&num=1&start=1&query=cylinder7130
- "I Laughed at the Wrong Time" (Cylinder EDI 0037)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison cylinder sound recording. The performer and ID number are printed as, Cal Stewart, 1852. There are some slight cracks to the plastic on the bottom edge of the cylinder. The plastic has also lightened and yellowed on the top one third of the cylinder. Paper is stuffed into the cylinder in the top. The case has no lid.
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and may be streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr+1=1020&num=1&query=cylinder4974
- "I'm Looking for a Sweetheart" (Cylinder EDI 0038)
  This is a Blue Amberol Edison cylinder sound recording. The performer is printed as Jones, Murray and Chorus. There is no legible ID number. There is some slight pitting of the inner plaster core on the edges. There is also some slight yellowing of the inner plaster core in places. The case has no lid.
  This cylinder has been digitized by UC Santa Barbara and may be streamed here: http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr+1=1020&num=1&start=1&query=cylinder7101
- "The Tales of Hoffmann-Barcarole" (Cylinder EDI 0039)